Finding Aid for George W. Baber Papers 1942-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George W. Baber Papers 1942-1970
Baber, George W. (George Wilbur), 1898-1970.
1 linear ft.
Bishop of the African Methodist Episcopal Church, pastor of various churches in Michigan and elsewhere. Correspondence, prayers and speeches, clippings, and programs; collected A.M.E. minutes, published material, and miscellaneous; and photographs illustrative of his career activities.
8538 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Elvira Baber (donor no. 7120 ) and came to the library through Reverend Kenneth Hill.
The collection is open for research.
Bishop George Wilbur Baber was born in 1898 in Cleveland, Ohio, the son of an African Methodist Episcopal minister. He attended Wilberforce University and was licensed to preach in 1919 by his father. Admitted to the Michigan Conference in 1923, he built churches and served as pastor in LaPorte, Indiana, Benton Harbor, Michigan, and Flint, Michigan.
In 1934, Baber became pastor of the Ebenezer A.M.E. Church in Detroit. Under his leadership, Ebenezer grew from 600 to 6000 members by 1944, making it the largest pastorate in the A.M.E. denomination.
At the General Conference of 1944, Baber was made 63rd bishop of the church. After brief service in Baltimore and Arkansas, Baber was assigned to the Fourth Episcopal District, encompassing Michigan, Canada, Illinois, Indiana, and Iowa. Then in 1956, he was reassigned to the First District, which ran from Philadelphia through New England.
Barber's final assignment was to the Second District in 1964. It included the District of Columbia, Maryland, Virginia, and North Carolina. Based in the nation's capital, Baber became vocal in national politics. He publicly called on A.M.E. ministers to back President Johnson's 1965 urban housing program. And in 1968, he was an active supporter of Hubert Humphrey.
Baber has been president of both the A.M.E. Bishops Council and General Board. He also served on the board of Kittrell College and as A.M.E. delegate to the New Delhi conference of the World Council of Churches.
Baber first married in 1918 to Alma Marie Wims who died in 1954. He remarried in 1955 to Elvira Mayfield Derrick. Baber is the father of two sons and three daughters.
The papers of Bishop George Wilbur Baber are divided into seven series: biographical, correspondence, prayers and speeches, clippings, programs, African Methodist Episcopal Church, and photographs.
Subjects:
African Americans.; Baber, George W. (George Wilbur), 1898-1970.; Clergy--Michigan.; African Methodist Episcopal Church.
Subjects - Visual Material:
African Methodist Episcopal Church.; Afro-American clergy.; Afro-Americans.; Agnew, Spiro T., 1918-; Baber, George W. (George Wilbur), 1898-1970.; Church vestments.; Clergymen.; Egypt.; Government officials--United States.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; India.; Israel.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Rites and ceremonies.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series consists of general background material on the life of Bishop Baber. Included are newspaper obituaries, awards and certificates, and a biographical pamphlet published in 1944 upon Baber's selection as a bishop.
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1945-1971
  All correspondence to and from Baber is arranged chronologically in the Correspondence series. There is some correspondence with individual church members, particularly before 1965. The bulk of the series begins in 1965 and deals mostly with the administrative operations of the church and Kittrell College. There is also correspondence with political and religious leaders dealing with political and philosophical issues.
  - 1945-January 1971, 12 folders (Box 1)
- Prayers and Speeches
  Prayers and speeches by Bishop Baber are found in the Prayers and Speeches.
  - Scattered documents (Box 1)
- Clippings
  Clippings series includes press clippings about Baber.
  - 1950-1970, undated, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Programs, 1957-1968
  Programs come from various events attended by Baber.
  - Scattered programs (Box 1)
- African Methodist Episcopal Church
  The African Methodist Episcopal Church series contains a variety of church papers and publications which do not relate directly to the life of Bishop Baber. Included are the minutes from meetings of church leaders, pamphlets and publications, and a chronological series of miscellaneous church papers.
  - Minutes
    - General Conference, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Council of Bishops, 1956-1966, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - General Board (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets, 1962-1972 (Box 1)
  - Publications
    - Missionary Magazine, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - Voice of Missions, 1957-1963 (Box 1)
    - The Anvil, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous A.M.E. papers, 1942-1968, undated, 5 folders (Box 1)
- Photographs
  Photographs include personal portraits, family photographs, award presentations to political leaders and others, portraits with fellow A.M.E. clergy, and photographs from Baber's trips to the Holy Lands and to New Delhi for a conference of the World Council of Churches. The series includes photos of Baber with political dignitaries, John F. Kennedy, Hubert Humphrey, Spiro T. Agnew, Nelson Rockefeller, and G. Mennen Williams.
  - Portraits of George W. Baber (Box 1)
  - With family (Box 1)
  - Award ceremonies (Box 1)
  - With religious leaders (Box 1)
  - Trip to Holy Lands (Box 1)
  - World Council of Churches Conference, New Delhi (Box 1)